So where were we in the last class we were
looking at.
Bellman I mean MDP s and you are taking it
the bellman equation right so the MDP is are
rectified by
right so this is what we use for defining
in MDP right and what is the bellman equation
let us stick with the bellman equation for
B for the simplicity sake tell me okay likewise
we had another optimality equation
right so we have the optimality equations
one thing which I want you to note about the
optimality equation is that we are making
an assumption that
so the optimal policy would have the same
max here right.
So that is fine correct another assumption
that you will make as we go long trying to
solve the MDP is that the optimal policy is
deterministic right so and we will also use
this following notation instead of saying
pi of a given is I will use the notation,
so pi of s given is essentially a single action
a that we will always do whenever you come
to state s right so by of a given s is a probability
distribution right this is essentially saying
that if my p is says that it is one for one
action and 0for all the rest for every state
right.
Then I can represent it as this is where I
will return the action for which the probability
is 1 okay so this is a deterministic policy
so this is a notation that you use so this
is the note sir right and later on well we
will see that will make an assumption that
the deterministic policy I mean the optimal
policy is deterministic right, in fact more
correctly you will assume that if the MDP
has an optimal policy then there exists a
deterministic optimal policy right there could
be multiple stochastic optimal policies but
that will exist at least one deterministic
optimal policy.
So that is assumption that will make so later
so in fact I will see if I can actually develop
all the machinery required to prove that but
we would not have to go do that right so we
will see if I do not get to that then please
take it on faith okay so a couple of things
so now I am going to talk about so the existence
and the uniqueness of solutions for these
sets of equations right going to talk about
the existence and uniqueness of solutions
for this set of equations so for us to get
into that we need a little bit of analysis
right.
So we need to know a little bit of knowledge
from functional analysis and so I will I'm
going to keep it very very light okay I am
not worried I am not going to do anything
very deep in this but for that people have
to recall all their things about vector spaces
and so on so forth remember vector spaces
right so vector spaces you have a set of elements
are closed under addition and scalar multiplication
right, so we are going to consider at some
point welcome to that so one way of thinking
about the value functions right.
In a finite MDP you can think about it in
a non-final a discrete state space also but
for the simplicity sake let us assume that
what I am going to talk about now is only
about finite MDP so what are finite MDP these
are MDP where s is finite right and is finite
both s and a are finite and we already know
that the expectation should be bounded right
so these are the three conditions that we
need is a finite MDP then s is finite a is
finite and this expectation is bounded so
if you think of a finite MDP I can think of
my value function as a vector in a size of
s dimensional vector space right.
So I can think of it as a vector which has
s components
in fact
so it is it is a space on which I can define
a notion of a norm that normally something
like a size of the you can think of at roughly
as equal to being size of the vector that
I can define a norm on this vector space right
but I am interested in using a specific kind
of norm on this space which we will call the
max norm right so people know norms so you
can think of it as this kind of some kind
of a measure of size right so let us put this
down here okay, so what if and only if x is
0 norm x is 0 right and Alpha X is alpha where
alpha is a scalar is alpha times norm of X
and this is the triangle inequality okay great
we have this now I am just seeing what notations
I should introduce for you.
So that is fine so people know all about vector
spaces okay so in vector space where you have
a norm defined on the vectors is called that
norm vector space ok so all of you know that
great.
So now I want to talk about something called
a complete normed vector space we all know
about water normed vector spaces so when do
you say it is complete okay, so for that we
need to understand something called was it
not Cauchy-Schwarz inequality really need
to understand what is called a Cauchy sequence
okay, so a sequence of course is something
like this okay right so what does Cauchy sequence
it says that okay.
For any real epsilon that you give me I can
find some point in the sequence ok beyond
which if you pick any two elements they are
within epsilon of each other selective says
for any epsilon you give me right so what
does this mean so this sequence should be
such that the successive elements are coming
closer and closer to each other right does
it make sense is a sequence in which the successive
elements are coming closer and closer to each
other.
So if every Cauchy sequence in a normed vector
space converges to a point in the vector space
right then you call the vector space as a
complete space X one X two the rescission
x1 and x2 will be greater than X two and X
three yeah so x one x two the distance will
be greater than explain extreme possibly it
should be can you further from the definition
of a Cauchy sequence the Cauchy sequence just
says the successive difference are getting
smaller and smaller and smaller does not necessarily
say there is a limit right.
Does not necessarily say there is a limit
it just says it becomes smaller and smaller
and smaller and smaller so you could have
a limit right that is outside the space that
you are considering it right so if you want
to look at examples of Cauchy sequences that
are not convergent go look at Wikipedia right
so there are enough material out there that
talk about all of these things right so you
could have them becomes smaller and smaller
and smaller right but the point to which they
converge might be a point which does not belong
to the space that you originally are defining
right.
So these kinds of things would happen because
when we are dealing with infinitely long sequence
in all kinds of crazy things happen okay I
should have noted down one such example anyone
can recall an example of the top of their
head non convergent Cauchy sequence something
is like 1 by n and it converges to 0 but then
we can define of space which excludes 0 right
can you can you define a vector space at exclude
0no then they have to come up with some other
example say something that converges to some
other value 1 -1 by x.
We converse to and now define a space that
excludes Monday so but that people get the
idea right so Cauchy sequences might not be
convergent in the in the domain that you are
operating in right so the if every Cauchy
sequence okay good so I think that is all
we need from that
so when introduced a few more vector notation.
So that we can translate all these bellman
equations into in to some nice underlying
vector space and then show some results there
okay so we already have VS a vector. So I
am going to define r pi s essentially I am
saying that what is the reward I will get
in state s for following policy pipe and what
is expected reward in state s for following
policy pie it makes life a little simple as
you can see some of this thing here I am kind
of compressing and writing it as a single
vector essentially the first term here right.
I have compressed it and I am writing it as
r pi s is okay which is the reward I expect
to get starting in state s and following policy
pi just like the immediate one-step all right
it is not it is not expected reward for return
we need the gamm v of pi just the one-step
reward that I will get starting from s following
policy pi, so likewise I am going to write
so this gives me the one step transition probability
under policy pi right I fixed policy pie right
so this will give me the one step transition
probability under policy pi so what is the
probability.
I will end up in state Jif I start from state
s and take one action according to policy
pi and there could be many ways in which I
can get to state J from state S right these
are the two things that
we needed and so just as an aside if I am
using a deterministic thing this becomes a
little easier so this will essentially be
the deterministic policy so at some points
it makes it easier for us to explicitly consider
deterministic policies so I am just writing
out the notation here so whenever I want to
use deterministic policies I might actually
switch to this notation the summation over
a disappears right.
So likewise here this will be just I because
only one action I will take under policy pi
right therefore the probability of going to
j from s is a probability of going to j from
s under that action pi of s just a notational
convenience okay so do not do not worry of
too much for it so one thing to notice this
r pi of s is s dimensional vector again so
r pi sorry r pi is dimensional vector and
pp is a s-cross s dimensional matrix it is
also a special kind of metrix is a stochastic
matrix.
So what is the stochastic matrix those are
rows add up to one and anything else all the
all elements greater then and equal to zero
okay so all the all the rows have greater
than equal to 0 essentially each row you can
think of it as a discrete the probability
distribution right they are the entries in
a row sum up to 1 and they all have to be
non-negative so basically they lie between
0 and 1 then so the normal essential we are
going to make is that gamma lies between 0
included and one okay.
This assumption we will make and if you think
about it that one step returned it I can write
it as I will come to that in a minute right
so what do you think this is so if you think
of an MDP right where I am making one decision
right so the decision is going to cost me
to make a transition to some state right I
will starting from some s okay making a decision
it is going to cause a transition to a state
J right there will be a reward along the way
and I also have a terminal cost or a terminal
reward for landing in j.
That terminal reward is given by the function
V so if you think of it this way so my entire
problem consists of taking only one step right
I pick a step I take an action I perform it
I get my choose an action we perform the action
I am going to make one transition and that
is it Island right in what will happen is
for that one transition I will get some reward
right and for ending in that particular state
J I am going to get some payoff for ending
in j right and that pay of lets say is given
by V then this is the total reward I am going
to get right.
So r is the reward for the one transition
and v is the final cost right and where I
am going to land up is determined by p pi,
now you can think of it as a one-step transition
function where the terminal costs is given
by V, so what we really want to do is instead
of assuming that there is an arbitrary function
V that is giving us this terminal cost we
want to find a function v pi right which in
some sense substitutes for the terminal cost
of following policy pi.
Right so we want a v pi that satisfies this
equation so you can see why v pi is a terminal
cost side so it is like what is v pi so value
I am going to get expected return and going
to get starting from the next state and following
policy pi, so one way of thinking about it
is my decision making problem ended with making
one decision then I made the choice according
to pi I stopped there and whatever in the
future regardless I am going to consider that
as one value and then add it to main function
so that is be fine so I am thinking take in
treating v pi as a terminal cost for a one-step
decision problem and then what I really want
v pi to satisfy it should be the total cost
right.
Now starting from here so this is essentially
the equation that I want to solve for v pi
so we'll come to we solve later this is the
equation I want to solve for V pi so people
are all onboard with this right and so you
can substitute that for R pi and this for
p pi and you write it out you see that it
is essentially this expression like I started
from this expression and simplified it there
but I wanted you to look at the other way
of interpreting this expression that is why
I started with this terminal cost interpretation
okay.
So if the terminal cost interpretation does
not appeal to you can do algebra start from
this expression which way wish I hopefully
convinced you in the last class is correct
right simplified you will get that expression
okay great so this implies that okay, as simple
as if I just took this to other side and took
multiply it by the inverse on both sides I
get this so what can you say about this matrix
is it invertible will remember determinants
anyway fine.
So well you know what the Eigen values are
IR all ones right and what about p pi it is
stochastic the largest Eigen value for a stochastic
matrix is 1 okay, so the largest Eigen value
for a stochastic matrix is 1 and I multiplied
gamma so the largest Eigen value is going
to be less than 1 so the whole matrix that
cannot have a zero Eigen value that for this
thing will be invertible it in there for there
exists a unique solution for V pi was it well.
So for stochastic matrices right the Eigen
values the largest Eigen value for a stochastic
matrix is 1 this is why I said this is a particularly
mentioned that this thing is a stochastic
matrix right because the rows all sum to 1
you can show with little bit of work that
the largest Eigen value for stochastic matrix
is 1 okay so I am multiplying it by gamma
which is less than one right so this whole
thing is going to be going to have an Eigen
value largest Eigen value which is less than
1 right and the Eigen values for I are all
one right so if you take the difference matrix
and try to find the Eigen values for those
right it cannot have an Eigen value of zero
right as long as the matrix does not have
an Eigen value of zero it is invertible.
This is basic linear algebra properties I
right so therefore this is unique there is
a unique solution to this and we are all set
correct so this is sometimes known as the
green equation but not always because there
is something else also called the greens equations
but not always because thter is something
also called greens equation I do not want
to write it down threr so this is one way
of showing that p pi is unique right sorry
r is equal to dimension for a unique solution
yeah, that must be equal to dimension for
it to be invertible okay right this is one
way of convincing people that this works right
so another way of convincing people is to
look at the whole dynamics of what happens
right in that equation right.
So think about something like this right I
start with some arbitrary function for v piI
start with an arbitrary guess for v pi okay,
so I plug this in here right and I am going
to solve this equation not solve there is
going to run this computation so I am going
to get another expression for I mean other
value for v pi let us start with some arbitrary
gates let us call it v not okay I will compute
this I will get say v one right and then I
will go back and plug v one back into this
expression okay I will compute this I will
get v two and I keep doing this iteratively
right I am going to claim that this will converge
to V pi.
Right we are going to make several claims
I am going to say I made several claims in
that statement first claim was is going to
converge so you can claim was third claim
is it is unique right so we already know it
is unique from this expression this thing
this thing we know it is unique but I can
also try to show it in a different way right
so I am going to show that it is going to
converge right and it will converge to be
v pi and that v p is unique right so then
I am going to do it this way is it makes it
easier for us to handle the optimality equation
as well later right.
So if I show you how to do this in the v pi
case it makes it easier for the stand in a
optimality equation later great so people
have heard me before know that I am going
dead slow today I would have normally finished
everything I wanted to do by now but I will
probably go to a second class because I wanted
to make sure that people get what is what
I am saying right so let us see so if you
have any questions or anything are you are
completely lost how many of you are completely
lost that us basic basically linear algebra
,basic linear so go do me a favor go Google
up relationship of Eigen values to invert
ability of matrices they probably get a stack
over flow okay.
I do no stack state exchange it stack exchange
is here no that is a stat exchange right yeah
you would probably get a stat exchange hit
on this yeah anyway so that is very basics
term right so you know about determinants
and products of Eigen values being equal to
determinant right so a matrix is not invertible
only if the determinant is 0 right and if
know the Eigen values 0 then the determinant
cannot be 0 therefore the matrix will be invertible
that convince you maybe a bit more okay.
Anyway right let us go look up so I am not
going to do basically in algebra now so let
us now take you kicking and screaming into
something more I need to erase this part which
part can a race okay so I probably end up
erasing this part so everyone has copied down
what this our pie and R pi and P pi rare right,
so everyone has it in the notebook so I can
erase this because I am going to use it but
I want that expression also to stay I do not
want a race that so everyone has this great
so I am going to erase it.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights reserved